I'm sorry! I apologize!
对不起 真的很对不起
I apologize for everything I did up until now.
我为我至今所做的一切跟你道歉
Please, forgive me!
求求你原谅我
I will free you.
我会放你自由的
I swear to Odin.
我对奥丁神发誓
Money... I'll give you money too. As much as you want.
金钱...我也会给你钱 你想要多少钱都可以
Not enough...
不够...
That's not nearly enough
差得可远了
to make up for the humiliation
远远不足以弥补
I've experienced up until this day.
我至今所积累的种种遭遇
For once, see what it's like to be a slave yourself.
就一次也好 你亲自尝尝当个奴隶是什么滋味吧
Otherwise,
不然
you will never understand the depth of my anger.
你一辈子都无法体会我究竟有多愤怒
All right!
好啦
I will become your slave.
我就当你的奴隶吧
I'll serve you.
我会服侍你
From today, you are the master
从今天开始 你就是我的主人了
and I'm the slave.
我才是奴隶
Please spare my life, Master.
请饶我一命吧 主人
Is that so...
是这样的吗?
You'll become my slave?
你要当我的奴隶?
Yes, gladly!
对 乐意之至
Well then,
那么
whether I spare you or kill you,
不管是要宰了你 或是饶你一命
I can do whatever I like.
我想如何就如何
That was long...
好久了...
Now then, it's time for a reunion.
是时候该重聚了
To think that
这样说起来
we won't have to go to Mr. Sverkel's place to borrow his horse anymore...
我们再也不用向斯威克先生借马了
What's wrong? Why the long face?
怎么了吗?为何闷闷不乐的?
Well...
这...
Have you already decided?
你决定好了吗?
Huh? Decided what?
什么?决定什么?
I mean, once we're free.
我意思是...等我们重获自由之后
What do you plan on doing?
你有什么打算?
Oh, that...
这个喔...
You two! Once you are freed,
你们两个 一旦你们恢复了自由之身
would you like to stay here and work as farmhands?
你们想留下来当农场帮手吗?
Hardworking people like you two are always welcome.
这里永远欢迎 像你们两个这么努力工作的人
That was a nice offer from the master but...
主人提出的建议实在是很不错
What to do...
有什么打算...
I've been a slave for too long.
我做奴隶做得太久了
Who knew I'd be so indecisive the moment I was able to
谁料得到 到了我终于 能够替自己做决定的时候
make my own decisions.
我会如此犹豫不决
That's surprising.
还真出乎意料之外
So staying here is actually
那么对你来说 留在这里
a viable option for you?
是一个可能的选项咯?
It's true that I don't get along with the farmhands.
我的确跟那些农场帮手合不来
But if I stay here,
但如果我留下来的话
there might come a time when Arnheid can get her
还有机会等到阿奴纳也重获自由
freedom too.
还能等到那一刻
I'm so surprised.
我还真意外
You like her that much?
你真的这么喜欢她?
Oh, stop! That's not what this is about.
住嘴啦 不是你想的那样
I just...
我只是...
You're late, Gramps!
你来晚了 老头子
Are you trying to kill me?
你想害死我吗?
Where's Gramps? He's not with you?
老头子呢?他没跟你们在一起吗?
Huh? Oh...
什么...
The old master hasn't returned?
老主人还没回来吗?
Not since he left for the field this morning.
今早他去田里之后就再也没见到他了
Damn it!
可恶
It's already time for dinner.
晚餐时间已经到了
He asked us to split the firewood, but...
他要我们劈柴 但是...
That's strange.
很奇怪
By this time he's usually--
他通常会在这个时候...
I didn't eat anything for lunch either! Damn you, Gramps!
我中午也什么都没吃 该死的老头子
What if I die...?
万一我死了...
Where are you going?
你要去哪里?
The field! Follow me!
去田里 跟我来
The field?
田里?
Gramps!
老头子
Come on!
振作点
I'm going to die
我会死在...
on the bed and not the field, huh?
这张床上 而不是田地里 是吗?
Me, of all people...
还真没想到啊...
It's open. Just come in.
门没锁 进来吧
Excuse me.
不好意思
Um, the mistress
那个...女主人
ordered me to come here.
要求我来这里
W... Wow!
-厉害了 -不是吧
We get
我们也可以...
to eat this too, Arnheid?
一起吃吗 阿奴纳?
Yes.
对呀
The old master said that I can make enough for all of you.
老主人说我可以连你们的份也算进去
I hope you like it.
希望你们会喜欢
I guess no one prays here...
我猜这里没有人要做餐前祷告吧
So delicious!
好好吃喔
Please eat, Old Master.
请用餐 老主人
Delicious!
太好吃了
From today, I will be here to look after your needs.
从今天开始 我就会待在这里照顾你的日常生活
Please ask me for anything.
有任何需要尽管吩咐我
Try this too!
也试试这个吧
Will you be staying at my house overnight?
你会在我这里过夜吗?
Yes. That is what the mistress has ordered.
对 女主人是这么要求我的
Okay, here you go.
来 请尝尝
If it doesn't suit your taste,
如果不合您的口味
please let me know.
就请告诉我
That's good.
真好吃
I don't want it. I'll eat later.
我不想吃 一会儿再说
I'm not hungry right now.
我现在不饿
I see...
好吧...
Don't mind him. Just stuff the spoon into his mouth.
别管他那么多 把汤匙往他嘴里塞进去就好
What?
什么?
Gramps is too embarrassed to say, "aah."
老头子不好意思把嘴巴张开
Get used to it, Gramps.
早点习惯吧 老头子
You have no choice but to
你别无选择
say "aah" and have them spoon-feed you until you recover.
在复原之前 你也只能张嘴 让他们用汤匙喂你吃饭
Did you just laugh?
你刚才在偷笑吗?
Uh, no...
没有...
I'm really not hungry.
我是真的不饿
I'll eat later--
我等一下再吃
I'm kicking all of you out!
我要把你们全都赶出去
I'll wash the dishes.
我来洗碗吧
No, I'll do it.
不用了 我来洗就好
I'm glad.
我很高兴
The old master seems to be doing better than I was told.
老主人的状况 似乎没有他们说的那么糟糕
And he doesn't seem to be
而且他似乎...
as scary as he's rumored to be.
也不像谣言说的那么可怕
Yes. Despite his looks, he's kindhearted.
对呀 可怕的只有他的长相 他其实心肠很好
Although he can be scary sometimes.
但有时候他真的很可怕
I can kind of see that.
这点我似乎也察觉到了
But...
但是
Honestly,
老实说
it's been so long since the last time
我好久没有像这样
I had so much fun while eating a meal.
开开心心地吃一顿饭了
Me too.
我也是
It kind of
让我有点...
reminded me of what it was like when I was free.
回想起还是自由身时的感受
I agree. Really...
对呀 这倒是真的...
Hey, Slave!
喂 奴隶
Is Snake here?
蛇在这里吗?
A runaway slave?
有奴隶逃跑了?
Yes.
对
Supposedly, three days ago from Kjallakr's farm.
据说是在三天前 从凯尔拉克的农场跑掉了
Kjallakr, huh.
凯尔拉克是吗?
He always treated his slaves badly.
他一向很会虐待他的奴隶
He got what he deserved.
这是他活该
Well, it's not that simple.
事情没那么简单
That slave killed Kjallakr and all his sons
那名奴隶杀了凯尔拉克和他儿子
and set fire to their house.
还放火把他家烧了
He's ferocious and very skilled.
他很残忍而且武艺高强
Kjallakr's uncle is offering three horses to whoever catches him.
凯尔拉克的叔叔拿出三匹马 作为悬赏抓捕他
What do you want to do, Boss?
你打算怎么做 老大?
Putting aside the three horses,
撇开那三匹马不说
we should still be a little cautious.
我们该提高警惕
You guys, starting from today, patrol the area
从今天开始 你们在巡逻的时候
in groups of three for the time being.
暂时保持三人一组
Even if you find him,
就算你们发现他的踪影
don't go out of your way to catch him.
也不要擅自行动去抓捕他
First, call for backup.
先寻求支援
When a person is backed up against a wall
当一个人被逼到墙角的时候
you never know what they will do.
会做出什么惊人之举 谁也无法预料
Look, that's it.
你看 在那里
That reflection was coming from the decoration on the sword.
那道反光是来自于剑上的装饰
What's up with him?
他是怎么搞的?
Is he sleeping?
他在睡觉吗?
Seems like it.
好像是这样
At first glance he looks like a beggar or pilgrim.
他第一眼给人的感觉像个乞丐或浪人
Isn't he pretty suspicious?
他相当可疑 对吧?
Very suspicious.
非常可疑
More like, lower your voices a little more.
还是说 你们小声一点
So he must be
那么他一定就是
the one who's worth three horses.
价值三匹马的那个人
There's no doubt about it.
那还用说吗?
Hey!
真行啊
Luck is on our side!
我们走运了
- Idiot! It's not that easy. - Hey!
-白痴 没你想的那么简单 -你们俩
- Whisper! - I heard he's pretty strong.
-小声点 -我听说他很厉害
It'll be fine!
没关系
- We can attack him in his sleep. - Whisper!
-我们可以趁他睡觉的时候偷袭他 -小声一点
We should call for backup, like Boss said.
我们应该寻求支援 像老大说的那样
Don't be a coward, Lizard!
别那么懦弱 蜥蜴
If we call for backup, we'll have to share our reward.
如果我们寻求支援的话 就得把奖赏分出去
I'm telling you guys to whisper!
我叫你们小声点
You don't even know his level of skill.
你连他有几斤几两都不知道
Where do you get that confidence?
你哪来的自信啊?
The reward is three horses.
奖赏有三匹马
Right now, we can get one horse each.
现在的状况 我们一人能分到一匹
That's what I'm talking about.
我想说的就是这个
Things don't work out that perfectly!
事情才不是你以为的这么理所当然
- Whisper! - Just cut up the horses
-小声点 -不如把马砍了
and eat a leg or two, you fatso!
把马的腿拿来啃吧 胖子
Excuse me, you midget?
你说什么?矮冬瓜
If you want to die that badly, go alone!
如果你想找死的话 你一个人去吧
I'll kill you first!
我会先宰了你
- Right back at you! - Whisper, you idiots!
-我才会宰了你 -小声点 你们两个白痴
Man, it's hot.
天啊 好热
Thorfinn, I've chopped quite a bit of wood.
托尔芬 我又砍好一批木材了
Can you pile it up?
你能它们叠起来吗?
Hey, Thorfinn!
喂 托尔芬
Sorry, just a little bit more.
抱歉 等我一下
All right.
好吧
What is Thorfinn doing?
托尔芬在做什么?
Oh, Snake is inside and reading the Bible.
蛇在屋子里读圣经
So he's eavesdropping.
他在偷听
It's for the old master, who can't read.
是念给老主人听的 他不识字
I see. I didn't know Thorfinn was a Christian too.
这样啊 我不知道 原来托尔芬也是基督徒
Actually, he's not.
其实他不是
But apparently, it's interesting to listen to.
但是 很显然那听起来很有趣吧
"You heard that it was said:
“你听过这种说法:
'You must love your neighbor
‘你得爱你的邻居
and hate your enemy.'
恨你的敌人’
However, I say to you:
然而 我对你说:
Continue to love your enemies
继续爱你的敌人
and to pray for those who persecute you,
替那些迫害你的人祈祷
so that you may prove yourselves sons of your Father who is in the heavens,
你就能证明自己 是住在天堂的天父之子
since he makes his sun rise on both
因为他让太阳同时从邪恶之地
the wicked and the good
和良善之地升起
and makes it rain on both the righteous
让雨落在正义之地
and the unrighteous.
和不公不义之处
For, if you love those loving you,
因为 如果你爱那些爱你的人
what reward do you have?
你得到的奖赏是什么?
Are not also the tax collectors doing the same thing?
税吏不也在做同样的事吗?
And if you greet your brothers only,
如果你只和你的兄弟打招呼
what extraordinary thing are you doing?
这有任何特别之处吗?
Are not also the people
这个国家的
of the nations doing the same thing?
人民不也在做同样的事吗?
You must accordingly
你一定也随之
be perfect,
是个完美的人
as your heavenly Father is perfect."
因为你在天堂的天父是完美的”
Is that so...
是这样的吗...
Jeez, that's asking a lot.
天啊 这种要求也太困难了吧
Gramps, I'm tired of the Gospels.
老头子 我厌倦了这些基督教教义
Let's read the beginning.
我们来读开头的部分吧
It's more interesting than this.
有趣多了
Hey, Gramps. What are you doing?
老头子 你在做什么?
You need the bathroom?
你想上厕所吗?
B... Barley...
大...大麦
I have to
我得去...
harvest the barley.
收割大麦
Remember I told you,
还记得我告诉过你吗?
we finished that a while ago.
我们之前就收割完了
Just go to sleep.
去睡吧
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
Gramps wet himself. Can you take care of it?
老头子尿湿了 麻烦你处理一下 好吗?
All right!
好的
Oh, I'll help too.
我也去帮忙
Gramps is going senile.
老头子开始失智了
I bet he doesn't have much time left.
我打包票他活不久了
- What?
-什么?
No way...
不可能...
He's well enough to be out in the field every day.
他强壮到能够每天去田里工作
That's right. He even goes fishing two to three times a day.
对呀 他甚至一天内 可以去钓鱼两三次
But he's old enough to have grandchildren.
但他的年纪也老到可以抱孙子了
Old people deteriorate the moment their legs give out.
老人家的腿一旦不行之后 他们就开始老化了
That being said, it won't be that soon.
话虽如此 倒也还有一段时间
He's taken good care of you guys, so make sure
他很照顾你们两个 所以你们务必
to return the favor while you can.
趁还有机会的时候回报他
Um, I've always been curious.
我一直感到很好奇
What is the connection between
你和老主人之间
you and the old master?
是什么关系啊?
Huh? It's not like we have any special connection.
什么?我们之间并没有任何特殊关系
I just want to take that book
我只是想在老头子翘辫子之后
and sell it once Gramps dies, that's all.
把那本书拿去卖掉 这样而已
All right, get back to work.
好了 回去工作吧
The sun is almost setting.
太阳快下山了
He's going fast. Is it one of my men?
他跑得还真快 是我的手下吗?
No, it's not.
不 不是
Hey, you there! Stop!
喂 你给我停下来
Boss!
老大
It's him!
是他
He's the runaway slave!
他就是那个逃跑的奴隶
He killed Lizard!
他杀了蜥蜴
Please catch him!
请抓住他
What? Are you serious? Damn it!
什么?真的假的?该死
My sword is in the house.
我的剑在屋内
No way...
不可能吧
Gardar!
哥达
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
I finally found you!
我终于找到你了
My wife!
我的妻子
"Freedom."
自由
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译:朱未耒